What did you, what did we discuss last, last session?
Last session was, what was it, it was going off, it was, it was like the limit orders and stuff again, how you don't necessarily need a lot of volume to skew the market in one direction.
What's that principle that you're referring to?
I don't know what the principal's called.
I know that it was to do with the market.
order limit ratio being one or greater than one right so which one has to be greater than the other
the market order has to be greater than the available liquidity at that price level
cause in that ratio no the the liquidity has to be more to do what to skew the market in in
one way all right so in terms of that market to limit order ratio that's the principle
so market to limit order ratio
oh that's the principle okay
yeah which is greater than one
so when the market
to limit so when the market
is greater than the limit order
or equal to it
price will move
do you get it
okay I'm just writing this one now
yeah
got it
so what that means is if there's a level
with liquidity there
if I wipe it with a market order
and I still have
volume left to fill behind the market order
I push price to the next level
to get the next available liquidity
you follow me
so that's what moves the market
market orders essentially
from that we can
you know from that we can
get from that
what I just explained to you
that it's only market orders that move the market
it's impossible for a limit order to move the market
can you think of one reason why
did you say it's because they only get filled out
the certain price
and they don't get slipped or anything?
Yeah, it's impossible
to have a limit order
filled out a worse price than it's setter.
Yeah?
Yeah.
So if I have a limit at price 10,
that means I want to sell at price 10.
I want to sell as high as possible.
It's impossible for me to get filled at price 9,
which is lower than my set price.
Limit orders of friction,
limit orders of liquidity.
If I place a limit order at price 10,
that means if and when price gets to price 10,
that order is available for a buyer
to come and take and match with
and providing that predictable immediacy
at price 10 for someone to come and take that order
and match volume with
my order becomes liquidity
is a price making order
as we discussed market orders drive
price okay so that's not all we discussed
I think that was relatively a small topic of last session
do you remember where else
there was
there was quite a few examples of it
no
so I was discussing
price going to the less liquid side
was definitely a big discussion
or part of the discussion last week
last session
what I was discussing is how
dealer behaviour
oh yeah yeah yeah I remember now
how dealer behaviour can cause
can cause sorry
a skewed book.
So with the
liquidity,
the sell liquidity and buy liquidity
is not balanced.
One side is weaker than the other.
So when more market orders
come in,
there's less friction on one side than the other
and price goes to that less
friction side.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, I remember now.
So just to validate or like
make sure you're using the term correctly,
when you say skewed liquidity
or when you say,
when you use the word skewed,
we're not referring to market orders, you know?
We're referring to where the orders are sitting.
The limit orders are sitting in the book.
If there's one side, the by side,
that's much, much, much thicker than the opposite side,
the cell side, which side is skewed?
Or, you know, which side is skewed in favour of?
Which side is thicker?
I just said it.
You said the buy side was more thicker, wasn't it?
Yeah.
So in which direction would I require more market orders to push price in?
More market orders?
so I'll visualize it for you
the buyers are only ever going to be beneath price
yeah yeah
so here's buy liquidity
and here's sell liquidity
in order to push price
okay so which direction requires
more market orders
than the other side
to push it that way
you sell side
the sell side
so more market sales have to come in
compared to the necessary market buys
to push price down
probabilistically
it's much more likely
price will go up
now imagine
you had this information available
so you could see that the
market is this way
the book is skewed this way
and I offered to you
I came to you to Zain and said
yo I want to sell you this asset
would you buy it or not
yeah I'd buy it
yeah
now
all right
good choice
that information provided by the liquidity book or the available liquidity
who has informational advantage over the rest of the market
who has that advantage arising from not only the order coming in
but also they have a better view of the available liquidity in the market as well
you said it was the companies wasn't it nope what company
oh I'm going off the last um last lessons stuff
It was a less lesson, yeah?
What do you mean by a company?
You said the people who have the information.
Who? Yeah, I'm asking you who.
Which type of participant has that information?
Is it a random trader saying at a home looking at the charts?
No.
It's a big participant, like a bank.
What is the bank doing?
They could be doing the same thing I'm doing.
A bank, theoretically, could be trying to buy the pound
because they're trying to make 10 pips.
with a one pipstop plus.
They're getting information quicker.
No.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So you said, yeah, I asked you a question.
You has an informational advantage over another.
I said, do I have it?
Because I'm a retail trader set at home.
You said no.
Then you said bank.
But the bank can be fitting any role.
They could be just doing what I'm doing.
If they're doing what I'm doing,
they haven't got the same information.
They haven't got, sorry,
they haven't got an informational advantage.
But there's a certain thing
that banks do in markets
which gives them that edge
and that informational advantage.
What is it?
They make them.
They're market makers.
Oh, the answer's market makers.
Yeah.
Because here's
me at home.
All I see is a bid and ask
and all I see is price chart.
Let's take a tier one institution,
a tier one bank,
the largest institutions in the world.
or arguably the largest, not institutions were the largest banks in the world,
they receive one million trades a day from different clients.
So one, two, three, four, five millions of times a day.
Who has more information about the market's direction, view, sentiment towards the market,
Tier 1 Bank or me at home?
Tier 1 Bank.
Why?
Because they have more links.
to say?
Not links necessarily.
Basically, this bank
can say, out of this one million
individual trades,
400 billion was brought
of pound this day.
For example, they could
say, across all
currency pairs, 3 trillion
of dollars was sold that day.
This hedge fund,
that hedge fund, this large,
large trader, all went short
the US dollar that day.
They could say that this guy
who's a mullah at your local
mosque who beats children up
decided to buy the US dollar that day
what do you think
the bank will think of this mullah
who beats children up
he's buying the US dollar when all the global
corporations are
or sorry all the large institutions are selling
the US dollar
no the person is going to lose
almost 100%.
Yeah?
So imagine the bank already has this information
then the mullah places that short trade
who has an informational advantage
the mullah or the bank
arising from
the information that
it knows how many
who's buying who's selling
so
okay so the order flow
the order flow is giving them information
now if they only received
one order a day
do you think they have that much of an edge
no
but if they receive millions and millions of orders in a day
now suddenly they
much more well equipped
and have a much better understanding
of where the market is likely to go
simply from the information arising
for Mordaflow.
Much, much more than me sitting at home.
Now, also, what's the tier one bank doing
when a million people are trying to trade off their prices?
How are they making money?
The good is spread.
Yeah? So here's a bid and here's a ask.
Now, let's go back to this original equation.
they know that 400 billion pounds worth of being brought
three trillion dollars have been sold
we're looking at gbp ust which side is likely to have a heavier liquidity
which side do they are they willing to provide a lot of liquidity on
sell side so you might have 40 million on offer there
and they're willing to so shit what am i talking about
sell side of pound so if pound's going down no i said
400 billion pounds have been brought that day
3 trillion dollars have been sold
Oh okay
Yeah then they're gonna want to buy it
The bid side yeah so the more likely gonna have
liquidity behind the bid
And less liquidity behind the offer
Yeah
Now I'm giving you a very generic kind of
Example here because in reality
It's not that one-sided
You have volume coming on on both sides
In a second it can change
Many many many times in a single day
the order flow at least intraday changes.
So you had bidding, bidding, bidding, bidding.
In this environment, let's just say the liquidity providers or provider or was receiving
40 billion bid pound and, you know, a lack of willing buying pressure for the, for the
USD.
They themselves would also adjust their bid and ask and have less liquidity on the ask price
and more liquidity on the bid.
because if someone hits their bid they buy
if someone lifts their ask price
they then sell to that someone
does the bank want to sell in this environment
when it's heavier buying on the pound
so their reaction to that
their reaction to like changing the available
liquidity in the ask price
doesn't it decrease the friction
present in this whole area
does it decrease in friction
yeah is there not less sell liquidity here then
if they if they themselves have less sell liquidity behind the offer yeah what do you think the
effect of that is when that buying then comes through there's less liquidity here now that buying
causes price to do what shift go skew in one direction no the book is already skewed so there's
thicker buy liquidity there's thinner sell liquidity here when buyers now come through and more
buy running comes through you know pop through it has to reach to find the sellers
exactly. So originally we had that 40 million bid, 40 billion bid. The liquidity provider
responds to this large volume coming in and reduces the cell liquidity, which then results in this
40 billion having to travel further than it really should to find cell liquidity, making this move
worse. So originally, big buy. Okay, price is going to go up. Liquidity provider responds to
a big buy and reduces sell
liquidity, reducing the friction
in the way. Price goes up even
more because of the behavior of the dealer.
Oh, okay. You follow
me. Yeah. So that's
an effect of our information
from arising from customer order flow can affect
the market in a specific way.
So yeah, we discussed
that last session. So
all I'd ask you is, last
session we would have discussed this, I would have made
this point, basically.
If it didn't make sense, if it does
If I talk about something, it doesn't make sense.
You don't understand what I'm talking about.
I ask, tell me.
And I'll try to restructure it a different way to make you understand.
Do you get it?
I'm giving you insight into how the dealer behavior here made this price move run further than it should.
And there's a certain effect of that.
So the result of that behavior makes price stretch further.
With price stretching further, something happens inside of this,
which is, you know, it basically,
results in a skewed book
basically at the end of it
and the effect of that skewed book is
thin by liquidity
much thicker
than liquidity at this very specific
point imagine like a snapshot
take a picture
the snapshot of the liquidity here
within that particular
microsecond would have been like this
it may have even been
where it has so thin
liquidity
even require a strong area of sellers.
Do you get it?
So take a picture of the liquidity state there.
You take a picture at that very precise moment,
the bi-liquity will be so stretched out,
which again will look at the infrastructure in a few moments,
where it doesn't even take a whole lot of sellers.
Actually, there doesn't even have to be a change in the available sellers.
Sell liquidity can remain thin at that point and still price drops.
Again, we'll define that in a bit.
So we're looking to identify these kind of skewed environments
because if I said to you, this is the book,
do you want to buy this asset when the book looks like this?
What do you say?
No.
If you want to sell the asset, you probably should sell it, right?
There's edge in trading under a condition like that.
Now, obviously, no way gives two folks about a four-pip move.
Okay.
but we'll be looking to like take advantage of this effect in the market
there's one option in how you can trade another option is when the imbalance is
present try to trade with it so when you know there's a large bid here or large buyers
here and thin liquidity here why is they thin liquidity there how can you see this
thin liquidity there we're reading it through price action I but
Oh, you'll see that with the price action bit.
Basically, there's a principle, another principle, that price reflects state of liquidity.
So when there is an imbalance, there's a certain visual structure that's present that shows us imbalance.
Okay.
When there's exhaustion, there's a certain specific type of pricing, ticking, so how much price moves, the rate of ticking, which can help.
is infer or interpret, that is exhaustion.
So, yeah, that question is a valid question.
We could read it on, we could read it on a order book as well.
It'd be present on an order book.
I don't know if you know what a thingy, what's this chart called, man?
A heat map.
There's something called heat map, where it shows you the liquidity in lines like I draw them.
Is that called book map?
book map is dots
it's very similar
heat map and book map
book map's just an extension of it
book map shows you where the trades were executed
heat map it also has a
heat map showing you the lines as well
now
let me pull up that fucking video
because it just shows you the liquidity
disappearing and price stretching out
if I can find it
so the point
I'm making here is the research
the necessary research about the infrastructure
and the trading
behavior and microstructure has already been done.
This question that you asked to be that how do I know that is an imbalance present
is obviously without you being able to answer that question,
it's almost impossible for us to take advantage of this, yeah?
There is a way to do it.
It relies on this principle that price reflects state of liquidity.
We're not necessarily there, yeah?
We're not talking about the visual structures necessarily.
I'm still introducing you to the dynamics behind, you know, price movement.
So when we get onto that, this principle and the introduction to the visual framework,
the different types of price action will be able to use these principles to define when there is
imbalance, when there's exhaustion, when there's a severe imbalance, all of these things
will be able to do through price.
Yeah, I just had to ask because obviously we're talking about it quite a bit and I'm thinking
How do you even know it's like that?
Yeah.
How do you know it's like that?
Okay, so I'll ask you a question.
What's going to happen in the next minute?
I have no clue.
All right?
What's going to happen in the next year?
Even more.
No clue, yeah?
Yeah.
So this idea of wanting to know what price is going to do is just irrelevant.
Oh, sorry, this idea of wanting to know the future with certainty is ridiculous, right?
it's inappropriate for something as random and complex
as at least what price is going to do next
so there's typically a tone that that traders that traders have
when they want to know the future and just because they don't
it's as if we're not able to trade it's it's not true that's not true
because over the next minute you have 60 individual seconds
each of those seconds we can actually
observe experience
linearly one after another
spread apart
with the exact
you know the exact same time
in between them
the microseconds
and over that time you can observe
changes no
yeah you can
right so
when this candle was forming
we'd observe certain changes within that candle
and each change provides us
new information
and if you observed
the way this
very very specific
thin move happens
the changes that occur
the sequence of events that happen
over this 60 second period
if you observed all of that
10,000 times
I'm telling you very
very early on you'll be able to at least
recognize what is to it
okay so
experiencing price and tracking it very closely
is one of the necessary things we have to do
to be update
sorry to be up to date
of all the incoming information
or the new things that are happening in the market
you simply have to be there to observe it
but anyway, that answers
one part of your question. The other part of your question
would be how do you know that there's an imbalance
there? Well, the market to limit order ratio
the definition of it
proves that there's an imbalance
after the fact we can observe them.
We're not necessarily there yet
trying to predict what's going to happen next, we're not doing that yet.
I'm just trying to explain to you
why price did that.
You follow it?
And the effect of why Price did that is one where you have a skewed book,
a snapshot picture there is like that.
So the market to limit order ratio,
if there's two ways that it mean you can transact,
a market order,
we can take liquidity,
limit order,
we can place liquidity.
There had to be by definition of a transaction,
which is going to be in the most basic books of market structure
that were first created,
when the first idea of markets came around,
I don't know how far back
the rules for these market and limit orders were created
so for price to have gone up here
there had to be a market order
that was greater than the available
sell limit orders here
if that wasn't the case
it's literally impossible price went up
you get it
so that explained you the part of your question
I don't know exactly what your question
was for to be honest
but how do I know this is it
imbalance because the rules of trading define, you know, the definitions of the rules and the
protocols behind the transactional rules for trading, you know, are the only reasons why price
would have shot up like this. There's no other definition. You can, you know, so we can look at
the structures and the rules behind why price went up, or we can sit here and say that market
maker number one, his dad has cancer, so he decided to raid ICT stop because he is evil
and because the sun rises in the west and because this happens and because that happens
and because the world is sad, you know, we can sit here and rationalize shit like this
or we can look at the specific rules under which transactions are formed and the effects
of those rules, the organizational framework, which
has to be met for price to rise
the same way
for you to be alive right now
your heart has to be beating
for your heart to be beaten
there has to be blood
you get what I mean
we're looking at the actual reasons
for why price goes up or down
and then of course
we're going to go into the branch of
exploring the effects
of price going up in such a way
I'm also discussing with you
why there was weak sell liquidity here
well
it's not like everybody's liquid
for me to obtain quotes
as a large institution basically
you don't go to your next door neighbor
and obtain quotes from them
you go to a market maker
whose job it is to give you quotes
they make the market for you
that market maker
sets quotes
and they also set the amount of liquidity
behind the bid and ask
and you follow me
So when the market maker responds adversely to certain risk, though they see a big, big, big bidder, $40 billion, for example, the market maker is not willing to go short.
They respond to that by adjusting the liquidity behind the ask price.
That then has another effect, a follow-on effect, creating less friction in the way.
So this original $40 billion happens to travel further or it ends up traveling further because of the behavior of the market maker.
The behaviour of the market maker is well, well documented in research papers that I can pass on to you.
Just the same way I passed on to you this, what confirmed what market to limit order ratio greater than one causes.
Price goes a less liquid side.
How there's an edge in that, how a certain Stanford educated guy researched, there's actually countless research papers out there that discuss,
dynamics of how market makers behave.
There's the head of FX.
His name's Raul Oman
in Docia Bank.
That's how you spell his name.
He in 2017,
2018 and
2019 published some very, very
recent papers regarding
how dealers, liquidity providers
deal with risk.
And in that, he even talks about
some of these things, about position skewing.
How this, basically
is well, well documented.
So, if you require,
obviously we can pass on the research to you.
But yeah, going back to what I was discussing,
there's a, there's a information effect arising from water flow.
There's a trader or market participant behavioral effect on the available liquidity.
We know that traders and liquidity takers need liquidity providers.
When the liquidity providers respond and liquidity, the friction of the way the liquidity
dissipates
it spreads out
the effect of the market
order is enhanced
it has to travel
further to find
counterpoys
right
and then of course
the effect of that
is what we're discussing
here anyway
so yeah
hopefully that
provides
somewhat of a
satisfactory
fucking answer
to that question
how do we know
you know
this is an imbalance
well it has to be
there has to have been
more market
orders and limit orders and how can we recognize this for now i just hope you can just
bear with me um will later be defining through principles that are validatable yeah anyway
it is it's very important you understand at least the theory you know the reason why i'm
discussing again this way is critical it validates what we're doing but um if i said to you
there was a very, very, at this very second,
unrealistic amount of liquidity here,
there was unlimited liquidity here.
Yeah.
So there was infinite.
Would this price move of be impossible?
No.
Impossible, right?
There had to be more market orders
than the available sell liquidity.
Yeah, for it to move up, yeah.
For it to move up.
Maybe that sell liquidity disappeared.
Maybe there was enough,
maybe there was unlimited.
that liquidity that minute
or that second
and then suddenly pulled away
that second.
It just disappeared.
And then after price pushed through,
maybe it turned into bi-liquity either.
So we can have a look at stuff like that
and the reasons behind why that happens
now, basically, when you go on to it.
So I'm going to start discussing with you
the structure of FX at least.
So let me just pull up.
Which one is it?
All right, cool.
So hopefully by this point,
You know, the difference between a market maker, a dealer and whatnot, yeah?
Yeah, yeah.
One minute please, bro.
Son of a bitch, I missed the trade, bro.
Would you have traded it at this time, though?
You said you have times?
It depends, like, right now, so when you first were discussing with me,
we were discussing how the market was in like a skewed, we were discussing,
yeah, basically the market volume dries off, yeah?
There's an effect of volume drying off, and sometimes it's tradable.
I typically like
I won't necessarily be trading
aggressively that actual day
I remember where it was
price had sold off very aggressively that day
and I said to you the market
the volume should dry off now
increasing the chance of price
drawing back into range
yeah yeah I remember you saying that
yeah
what price did is taking over leg lower
and it drew back into range
for the rest of the night
and because I was down
like a two tenths of a percent that day
I was willing to trade at night
today is a bit more
of a different environment. It's not a heavy direction all day. Rather, it's a quite a stable
environment. Imagine if I said to you, there was nice sell liquidity and enough sell liquidity
there, there was decent buy liquidity beneath price. When the market order buyers reached
the sell limit orders, they were drying off. When the market order sellers reached the limit
buyers, the sellers were drying off. So all day, between this relatively 50-pip, 60-pip range,
there was relative stability in the market
to limit order ratios on both sides
there was sufficient limit orders
to absorb the market orders on both sides of the market
all day
within this environment you have
it's the best environment
like I said if price never changed from this
I'm telling you I'd be a fucking multi-billionaire
I'd be betting cracker's lives
people's mom's mortgages
everything
but everything would be better on this
but it's not the case
so yeah when
the market environment is like this I typically
I milk it if you've ever seen
RM post nice orders
and nice like consistent trades
time minute after minute hour after hour
that's a range first
so not even look
this whole move down
it's composed of obviously there's ranges
so range move
move for a very very short
period of time, start ranging again.
Move for a very, very short period of time,
start ranging again. So it's not
necessarily a range
per se. It's, you know,
on one scale, you could define this as
a range. On another scale, you could define this
as a bearish trend. Are you trying to show something?
Oh, mad.
Oh, I thought you was just talking and
just, oh, okay.
Yeah. So
the point I originally
said to you, imagine there was sell liquidity
above price, there was bi-liquity above price.
every time price reached down here the market order sellers couldn't be the market order
the market order sellers were not outnumbering the limit order buyers and when price reached
up there up there the market order buyers were not outnumbering the limit order sellers yeah
so within this 65th range there was relative stability the market orders
were hardly ever basically within this range there was sufficient liquidity limit orders
to absorb all the market orders, buying and selling.
You follow me.
So within this environment, there's very unique behaviors we see.
Then you said, you rightly said, RM takes advantage of ranges
and he trades very actively in ranges.
To me, simply calling it a range is a bit too like...
Simple.
Not simple, the definition of range is too tight.
Okay.
Because the point I'm making,
is on one hand, yeah, it's a range.
On the other hand, one could say it's a bearish trend.
Yeah?
What I'm looking at is the tempo, the rhythm,
rhythm, I think that's how you spell it,
the tempo and rhythm of this trend.
It's not smack, smack, smack, smack aggressive.
I can show you that.
I'll show you that right now.
There you go.
There's a bit of a smack there.
This is what you call a decent,
quite an aggressive sell-off.
And then here's what you call a more stable,
more stable tempo
you get it
so simply calling something
a trend there's a down move
simply calling something a range
it's too
it's overly specific
it's not appropriate for the market
which you know a trend could be like this
a trend could be like this
right every single
one of those examples
have different implications
on how you can trade it
even though
All of these are the same thing, no?
That's a bearish trend, that's a bearish trend, that's a bearish trend.
So when you look at it with this singular,
through this quite a tight prism,
you kind of ignore the necessary details.
And yeah, you can just make you,
you basically ignore critical information.
That information is valuable.
Yeah.
So at this time of day, because of this current environment,
I'm willing to be quite active.
Do you get it?
I've sat here from, I think I work about 4.30, they went to sleep.
Basically, I've got to charts about 5.30, 6.
I've sat here from then, caught this low.
I didn't catch this high.
I didn't catch that high there.
I caught the retest.
I caught this low here.
And then basically I just got tired.
I just got tired.
It seems like it was a successful day.
A good day, yeah.
like I said to you I don't really risk more than 0.2% on the trade I don't really get that excited
trading anymore it's just like I recognize this environment and I take advantage of it because
preceding this environment we had this super aggressive sell-off which isn't that favourable to trade
yeah you told me that um it's not likely well there's more days where um prices is like today
than it is breaking out
how you explained how
the breakout traders
they love it for a couple of days
and after that they're getting smacked
their edge has been eradicated
or eroded because of like
changes in the market structure
that's at an effect on how much the market breaks out
so yeah like I'm not necessarily
a breakout trader this times
or I'll be short from the top
I'll close the majority of my trade and I'll write it down
so I have no pressure
and having to be active
but if you've got no exposure in the market
you're sitting there for days on end
with your balls in your hand
sometimes you want to be active in it
so typically in this environment
I'll be trading early early early
early in the morning or late in the day
I won't be trading in the middle
yeah okay early in the morning
late in the day
here I'll be morning
middle fucking end of day
it doesn't really matter
okay so that's why
answers my question
yeah
a lending institution, and then you have the customer segment, so the bank customer segment.
Now, the way it kind of works is that, all right, so any market that exists is based upon
tradition, the rules behind it, the custom behind it, it's all just tradition.
Imagine, you know, me and you or a large business, Apple, had to transact one million today.
How unrealistic is it?
to sell $1 million
and buy $1 million worth
of Japanese yen, which is going to be hundreds
of millions of yen. Yeah?
How unrealistic is it
to have that money exchanged within minutes
or seconds?
Yeah, one million. It's quite unrealistic.
Yeah? So what happens
in FX at least is an idea
of where the tradition is
the trade is entered,
is opened, but the trade
is settled T2.
Two days.
All effects transactions, real money transactions,
they're settled in two days.
That's a tradition.
So the bank will actually exchange money with Apple two days later.
The initial transaction is done based upon Apple's relationship with the bank.
The bank knows Apple.
The bank knows Apple's quite liquid.
The bank knows Apple has a lot of fucking dollar with them.
So they're willing to give them two days worth of,
they're willing to not exchange money with them for two days.
Do you get it?
and still open the trade for them so that's an example another example is why would apple go to a
bank to exchange a million and not to the local fucking supermarket or to their local billionaire
because a bank has certain regulations they abide by to keep them safe to keep client money safe
why do you house your money with a bank and not with the local committee yeah because it's safe
Get it?
Yeah.
It's fucking safe here, isn't it?
The governing body is a central bank, all right?
A central bank kind of has two governing bodies.
Something called a bank of international settlements.
It's not really a governing body, but they do kind of work together closely.
And obviously, the government, the government can set and take rule away from central bank.
But anyway, I don't want to go into too much of the banking system because it is a fucking whole different topic.
What is a bank?
you place 10 pound with them or I place 10 pound with them
they owe me 10 pound no
yeah but they took 10 pound of my cash
it goes into into an account that says 10 pound owed
so basically they have they have the actual
asset there which is the actual 10 pound cash
but they also have a liability minus 10 pound o to s
what they can theoretically do is take that cash
and lend it out to Zane.
So they only had originally
10 pound, but they owe me
10 pound, and because they borrowed
you 10 pound, basically they owe you 10 pound
as well. How can they only be
10 quid,
but they owe 20 pound.
Yeah, I don't know.
Basically, it only works if
Zane actually ends up, so this is how
it has to work. Zane comes and takes
that 10 quid out, is gone. The cash
is gone, the 10 pound debt's
gone. As long as I
you don't come out back and try to get that 10 pound off them it works no okay imagine yeah yeah
if zane pays the money back in two months time that debt's gone oh shit oh shit they have an asset
called a debt by the way so the cash is gone but the asset that that zane owes as a debt is still class as
asset so zane comes back pays the debt that that debt's gone the cash comes back they
probably charged you one two percent whatever you got that one two percent from
probably investing in farming equipment or or you know extracting milk from
buffaloes in a more efficient way is you came up with a new tool that made
you some money you made a few percent on it you paid a few percent for that
ten pound loan you gave the original ten pound back now the banks made some
money and the original ten pounds back and they could pay me if I want my
money back.
Yeah?
What happens if Zane still has the money?
Zane hasn't paid the debt back yet.
And I come and I want my money.
They haven't got the cash on hand to get that.
Yeah.
What do they do?
You get it?
Yeah.
Now imagine if that happened, I came.
I couldn't get my cash from them.
They said, wait, you have to wait six months.
Nobody would want to keep money in banks anymore.
And everybody would get their money out.
It's called a bank run.
It happened, I think, nearly in 2008.
So banks to maintain their business
They have to borrow off each other
You get it
Zayn has the cash now
You have the 10 pound
They owe me 10 pound
They have no cash on board
They only have this debt piece of paper
On our hand
So I come
I want my 10 pound back
This bank hasn't got it
They go to their bumchum friend
Bank 2
Bank 2's got 60 quits sitting there
Doing nothing
Then borrow this bank 10 pound
The bank gives me the 10 pound back
you follow me
so these banks borrow off each other
the fact that the bank is lending out
10 pound and making 20 pounds
worth a debt from it
that debt Zane owes the bank 10 pound
is classed as money as well
they're creating new money
that's why they call it banks can print money
right
they're essentially creating money
by creating debt
it's called fractional reserve lending
for fractional reserve lending to work
banks need to borrow each other
you know, this bank was illiquid.
It couldn't pay me to 10 quid it owned me.
So it had to get that liquidity from the other bank
by borrowing it overnight.
All of this, basically, I'm going down the line of saying
your domestic banks do that.
And also, you have something called
Tier 1 Capital Banks.
These are global international banks,
much, much bigger than Lloyds and your domestic banks.
Banks like Deutsche Bank,
J.P. Morgan, I guess.
H-S-P-C
what else
you can probably imagine
yeah
Goldman Sachs
all of these
are Tier 1 Capital
banks
which have multiple
services
but one of them at least
is issuing credit
right
now tier one capital
means
it's the highest
form of credit rating
you can get
the best form
as a bank
they abide by
very very strict
you could say
to the only this is not
but
they abide by very
very, very strict regulations about how much cash to have to keep on board, you can't just lend
out all the cash deposited to you, right? If I came and deposited five, five pound with you,
you can't lend that whole five pound out, because if tomorrow I want one pound back,
you need some money there. Maybe you can only lend out three of that five pound, because it's
unrealistic that I'll come and ask for the whole fibre. Probability-wise, I might only come and ask for
two pound at a time. So the other three-pound you're sitting there, you lend out, you try and make money
office. Do you get it? So that's what you call
reserve ratio. You have to have a certain amount of money on board. The regulations
are set by very, very, basically by something called the Bank of International
settlements. And all of these banks who abide by it,
who are highly, highly capitalized in the trillions, they're worth
at least, the whole investments worth trillions, they're called
Tijuana banks. It's these Tijuana banks that are the primary
liquidity providers in the world.
So if we looked at the operations of a single
Tier 1 bank,
they would have a segment for wealth
management. Oh, you know what? Make it a circle
because it's more accurate.
They'd have a segment
for wealth management.
They'd have a segment for investment
banking. They'd have a segment
for something else.
And they'd have a segment for
domestic lending or conventional
banking or domestic lending or
whatever. Do you get it?
we're primarily focused on the investment banking side
wealth management is basically they'll take on some
Chinese bastard money and they'll manage the money for them
they'll take on some rich motherfuckers money they'll manage the money for
corporate treasury a large corporation
Apple has business in the UK it has business in the US
they need two bank accounts in each country Apple
doesn't really want to wait three days
to have money sent from the UK to the US or US to the UK
So if they apply for treasury services from a bank,
the bank will have the accounts for them
and send over money almost instantaneously for them
should they need it.
Do you get it?
So they handle Apple's money for them in different countries.
And then like lending as well,
they'll be lending money to large corporations.
They lend money to Apple.
If you look at the lending rates in global economy,
If you're classed as like the largest corporations, Tesla, Apple, da-da-da-da-da-da-A-A-A-A-A-A-A-A-A-A-A-A-A-A-A-A-A-D-A-A-D-A-A-W-E-E-Q in basically an unequal way.
You basically get free money.
You can borrow a free, essentially.
It's very, very cheap you borrow it for.
But then if you're like a small, what do you call it, SME, a small mid-sized firm, I think is what they call it,
your interest rate suddenly shoot up.
So you're a local, you're a small, you're a small, you're a small,
business, a local takeaway or
I don't know, you do some local shit
you're a small firm, your interest
rates that you can borrow the money from the bank off
are fucking ridiculous
and that alone
skews the chances of you surviving
compared to the Apple
just because they're bigger.
The same way, if I earned
a million, I only earn
$25,000, you would actually get
access to cheaper money even though it doesn't
make sense. Yeah, okay.
right so anyway we're focused on the investment banking side now in investment banking basically
the the idea i'm laying out here is these banks don't need to trade effects all right anyway
we'll look at that so in investment banking inside of it well you have apple 50 how many years
ago they had some shareholders private shareholders they wanted to raise money they didn't need to do
an IPO initial public offering how do apple fucking know the
private shareholders know that the public wants to buy Apple.
Well, maybe they hire the services of an investment bank to go do the market research
for them, to even market Apple for them.
So when it comes time to start selling a certain percentage of Apple shares to the public
market, the investment bank already has the buyers there ready, they have the infrastructure
ready, they have the hype around Apple already, you follow me.
So the investment bank inside will do IPOs for large corporations.
They'll do mergers and acquisitions.
So when Apple, let's say, wants to buy their competitor, let's just say, in a very, very weird world, are they going to buy Google?
The investment bank would facilitate that transaction.
And then you have liquidity providing services.
What about when a client of Apple, a client of this bank, this Tier 1 bank, wants to access liquidity in large amounts.
so when Apple wants to
you know
shift off
$3 billion worth of
of currency risk
well the bank will do it for them
by that what I mean is if Apple's holding
$3 billion in risk
whose risk is it
what is the risk actually
3 billion isn't it
have you had 3 billion in your account
what's the risk
3 billion pounds in your account
well depends how much
no the simple risk is
it starts devaluing, no?
If you had four properties worth
20 million each, if the property
prices went down, what's the risk?
But you're now losing money.
Obviously, it doesn't really matter to us
when it's 1,000, $10,000,
20,000, even $80,000, it doesn't really matter,
but as soon as you start hitting big numbers and you're holding big
cash, there's currency risk involved.
Especially, especially if
Apple operates in Japan and they have
500 million's worth of Japanese yen,
they're not going to fucking book their profits in Japanese yen
they have to book it in the US dollar
yeah so what if Japanese yen
starts to increase in value against the US dollar
that's good for them
because that 500 million buys more US dollars
and then they're earning more US dollars no
yeah that's a good thing for them
but equally the risk is the US dollar source
appreciate and aggressively against Japanese yen
they're holding a shit asset
who's going to take that risk off them
Well, the bank does.
That's a large, large FX transaction
that had no speculative intent behind it.
Anyway, so in simple terms,
these banks, they have very, very tight credit relationships
with each other that require no deposits,
that require no collateral,
and they'll borrow to each other overnight
for no collateral at all.
Why? Because if this bank needs money
to pay out a certain client
to do this
to meet their financial obligations
their liabilities
if they don't meet the liabilities
confidence erodes
so they might need to borrow from bank too
are you following me
so there's that
they have tight tight credit
relationships with each other
very very important
in the banking side
in the investment banking
FX
liquidity provision side
it's literally as simple as this
these motherfuckers have whole or they have sales teams they actually have sales teams that know less than markets and price action and candlesticks than you do selling fx products to clients so when apple rings guess who's on the opposite end of that call the account manager when a new small medium size firm rings not medium size i say it's relatively big yeah let's say it's fucking fedex or dpd
They're relatively big.
When they ring and they're looking for quotes, they ring the sales team.
The sales team, they have a basic knowledge about the products that the bank offers.
Because FX, again, just to give you an idea of what the structure is, it's not just spot transactions.
If it was spot transactions, out of the $6 trillion a day that's traded, I think spot is like $2 trillion.
It's not the main part.
you have fx swaps and fx forwards forward the basically currency futures traded off of exchange privately
and swaps are basically a derivative financial product that decreases risk for certain
basically for like companies who want to hedge risk yeah and then spot fx is where me and you trade
is where large companies might want to exchange company cash straight away that day right then
where hedge funds might trade pound for certain reasons, et cetera.
So each of these, you might have one bank that specializes in forwards.
You might have one bank that specializes for corporate transactions.
You might have one bank that specializes in e-trade electronic trading platforms
for spot-fx transactions.
Do you get it?
And that's kind of the direction more recently at least.
Certain banks are specializing in certain things over each other.
but the point I'm raising here is the sales team
they have knowledge of these products
they sell them just like you
you know I don't know
insurance companies sell insurance policies
the the point I'm making to you is
these banks are raising money
not by trading markets and pushing them against you
and be like yeah Zane has a stop plus
of one lot at 0.0045 pipsom of price
let's take him out bro
These banks are raising their money on transactional-based revenue, on service-based revenue,
and they're doing it with the largest of the businesses in this whole world,
and they do it very consistent.
They have relationships with these large businesses.
So when Apple's servicing quotes from one bank, two bank, three banks,
bank one consistently wants Apple's flow.
So Bank one has to maintain a very, very, very,
tight, trustworthy relationship
with Apple themselves.
Apple actually has the
kind of, you know,
the leeway to say, oh, fuck you law,
I want to trade with this bank. What can you do
for them? Do you get it?
These guys are, in a sense,
service providers.
That's all they do. So,
credit relationships, sales teams,
sales floors,
and more and more
in recent years, automated
execution, so automated
it's like pricing engine and trading system.
So explaining the history
behind it. FX
is this
body of water.
Yeah? It's like a sea.
And then you have one country here.
You have one country here.
How does a company in the middle access this country
and move from that country to that country?
They have to go through the fucking river, yeah?
Or the sea. The sea
is FX.
The point, again, the implication of what I'm saying
here is, FX is
FX is not like a risk asset
where me and you buy it and make money off it
and me and you sell to whatever
it's not real estate where we invest
to make huge huge sums of money over the next 20 years
FX as a primary function
is a conduit
market
something that lets you access something
where global trade
the global economy
everyday functions of the economic
system that we live in
relies upon. It's essentially
you could argue some of the plumbing
of the financial system.
And it's composed of the providers
of the boats.
Those who provide the boats,
they take on the risk of maintaining
those boats, I guess.
They probably have the teams on the boats
and they're the service provided,
the banks. They're called
sell side. Why? Because they sell
liquidity. So they're sell side firms.
And then you have those who buy liquidity.
which could be a government, a hedge fund, a pension fund, the corporation, me, you, my dad, anybody.
Sorry, not me and you, because we're retail traders, yeah?
Sorry.
But if you owned a very large business that had direct relationships with the bank, then you become a buy-side firm.
If you one day set up a proprietary trading firm, you're a small buy-side firm.
Do you get it?
even if a buy side firm sells the pound they're still buying liquidity even though they're
short in that position to sell something you need liquidity the bank provides the liquidity
the bank is the service provider so I'm going to be using these terms sometimes so it's
important that you recognize them buy side buys of liquidity sell side sellers of liquidity so yeah
these are sell these are buy liquidity these are sell liquidity yeah cool uh basically I would know
What I was saying is the FX market is a conduit, right?
It's historically been this market that people use to access other assets in different countries
rather than it be in this type of asset class where me and loads of other speculators come together
to trade the activity as if it's like this asset that yields a lot of money.
It's not.
It hasn't been.
A very, very small percentage of FX is actually speculative.
Even hedge funds trading FX or if there's a hedge fund that has,
$50 billion worth of risk in U.S. equities.
In other words, they're long $50 billion worth in U.S. equities.
That means they're also 50 billion long U.S. dollar.
If the U.S. dollar starts dropping in value,
they're now essentially losing money on their, basically money they've got inside the U.S. stock market.
So they need to hedge that $50 billion risk.
They need to sell some dollars to make sure if the dollar start dropping,
they make some of that money back.
They fix their costs.
You get it?
So hedge funds trading FX, they can be largely just hedging trades,
not even speculating where the pound is going to go.
Corporations, again, they just do it for logistical purposes.
Every single day they need to transact.
Pension funds, again, it's going to be more hedging risks that they've got.
They might own, again, a good multistical.
million dollars worth of or pounds worth of government bonds, they need to hedge some of that
currency risks, so they use the FX market.
Governments as well, they need to maintain certain levels of reserves of other currencies,
especially US dollar.
They might even need to do direct transactions with US government or US central bank to keep
a certain level of FX reserves, so they need to transact in the FX market.
Sometimes.
Anyway, and then you have prime brokerage clients, which is any of these.
Okay.
But anyway, I want to keep going down some of the history of effects because it is quite important that we discuss it.
Historically in 1980s, obviously it was the same thing where you'd have a client.
He'd trade with the bank.
Why would he trade with the bank?
He needs immediate liquidity.
So bank, he buys off bank.
bank sells to client you get it yeah that's in the second tier of the market the tier two like I said
but the bank obviously is part of the interbank the bank has a short position yeah they have some
inventory they don't want to just hold a short position forever and ever and ever in 1980s again
you can just imagine the amount of liquidity the amount of frequency and transactions the amount
of volume traded per day would almost be nothing compared to what it is today they might even be
holding onto this risk for two, three days.
They need to get rid of that risk.
So they would typically offload it with a bank between themselves within the interbank market.
That's what it's called interbank.
Banks trading between themselves.
Now the problem with this was the structure through which they did it, isn't like they clicked on a computer, they found a quote from bank to and they just traded with them.
There was phone broker.
It was voice broken.
When the client traded with the bank, it was through a voice broken.
system where the bank tries to
offload some currency with bank too
there was also voice brokered
now the problem with fx trading
or any type of trading
is you need credit relationships with each other
you can't come to me and tell me that you want to
sell me a million pound and that you'll
give me the million in two days time
if I don't have a credit relationship with you
you just can't tell me that
I have to trust you you have to have proper formalized
relationships for me to even
consider you know
so when a bank
wants to trade with a bank
they're not trading straight away the exchange of the cash
especially in 1980s
they had to have the necessary
credit relationship with each other they had to have
that connection with each other where
if bank wanted to want to sell this guy
money or sell this guy's
currency he'd be able to do it
but they obviously had to confirm that
credit relationship exists
maybe in 1980s it was a
fucking file somebody had to check
sitting in an office
so imagine
here's a potential trade
bank one
rang bank two
got the trade
confirmed
and they obviously
they were short
so they brought that
they brought that currency back
balancing
balancing their position
you get it
now before that trade
is actually transacted
in two days time
some little fat woman
that's sitting on a desk
has to make sure
that these banks are connected
internally at both banks
so there's one fat woman
here there's another fat woman she wears sandals at the second bank it comes across their desk
they probably have to pull out of a filing drawer to check both of these are actually have those
fucking relationships yeah inefficient it takes too long this guy has short currency risk it takes
fucking this long to make sure that this transaction is going to happen it might take to the end
of the day and by the end of the day the currency might have moved quite a bit you get me so this
voice brokered, lack of credit
intermediation, lack of credit
checks, was quite an inefficient way of trading.
There was a gap in the market to make this more efficient.
No?
Yeah.
In 1992, a company called EBS,
electronic brokering services,
and Reuters trade matching, I think it was called.
Let me have a look. No, FX spot matching.
Yeah?
By, owned by Reuters.
these guys set up, as you can just imagine,
an electronic platform just for the interbank banks, interdealer banks,
that would connect all these banks together through this central platform
where they didn't need to ring each other directly anymore.
They could just go trade through this electronic system.
Guess what this system was?
It was a single order book similar to an exchange
where you post real orders on here, real liquidity,
and it operated like an exchange, basically, right?
Where when Bank One wanted to trade with Bank Two,
no fat woman had to check they had the credit relationship with each other.
The EBS system would already do it for them pre-trade, not post-trade.
Because the trade happened here already, and then the fat ladies had to check.
EBS will do it pre-trade.
It made it much faster
and much more efficient for banks to mitigate risk
and offset risk in 1990s.
991, 992 or 19992 or 993.
These two electronic systems were set up.
The problem here is
you now have these third-party companies
coming in, pushing their way
into the dealer market,
into the inter-dealer market,
and kind of becoming integral to the infrastructure.
is that me coming into your house
and I'm like, yeah, you have to install
this certain type of plumbing.
And it's my fucking plumbing.
You get it?
They took some market share away from banks, obviously.
Now, it's very important
to realize the credit intermediation that EBS did
solved a huge amount of problems for banks.
They effectively were able to offload currency risk
or offload inventory risk,
much quicker, much faster, results again
less money lost.
Actually, maybe even capturing more money.
of the transactions.
In exchange, obviously, EBS took some market share away from them.
Now, what eventually ended up happening is, over the next five, ten years,
is that most of the volume traded was already in between banks anyway,
and it was all being done for your USD on EBS and for GDPUSD on FX spot match.
So these became the primary price and liquidity exchanges
for the two most traded, for like all the main traded currency pairs.
U.S.D. JPI, U.S.T. Swiss franc.
It would have been on one or the other here.
Each bank specialized in one or the other currency.
So maybe one bank operated heavily on your U.S.D on EBS.
they obviously had some exposure on the other Reuters spot match
but the point I'm making here is we saw a slow migration and change
in how prices are made from banks just quoting quotes to the customers
willy-nilly in 1980s you ring the bank
the salesperson on the bank decides okay this guy's a retard let's quote him
a hundred pips spread this guy's less retarded let's quote him a 20 pips spread
you follow me
to prices being made originally
on the interdealer platforms
in a exchange-style way
so you have a single order book
this is EBS
all the banks trading amongst each other
are trading through EPS
so you have a limit order sell
a limit order buy that makes the best bid best offer
you have a single order book
where all the liquidity is posted here
all the liquidity is posted here.
So if I want to access as a bank,
an interbank,
a tier one bank,
$20 million,
I'll be able to see if it's all here,
rather than have to segment it from
for the banks individually
and have to get the credit checks done.
Can you just imagine how much more efficient it became?
It was really, really good, basically.
EBS matched the trades automatically.
It operated like an exchange.
In other words,
if all the liquidity is here,
or let's say 90% or 70% of the liquidity,
and volume is being traded on EBS,
where are the prices being set and made?
You know, where is the Euro-USD price changing and being made
if most of the trading is happening here?
Inside there?
Yeah, on EBS.
So the Euro-USD prices that you see on your charts
would have been being made on EBS.
Yeah.
All right?
Now, the way it worked.
You had Bank 1, Bank 2, Bank 3, Bank 4.
I'll just do it separately here.
They're all connected to EBS, but they also, that's the interbank, and then they also have clients, client, client, client, client.
They would look at the best bid, best offer changes on EBS.
So if price went up by one pip, price went down by one pip, price went down by four pips, whatever, the information that was occurring on EBS would result in them change.
in their prices that they update to their customers.
Think about it previously.
These banks were connected individually directly to each other.
So they were just quoting whatever quotes they could get access to
and obviously based on the customer.
But now because of EBS, there's a single quote
that all these other guys are looking at the same quotes being set amongst each other
and it resulted in a better, you know, what do you call it,
better distribution of prices
to the second tier of the market
a more fairer distribution of prices
to the customer segment of the market
now there is a reason why I'm talking about this
when a dealer
offloads certain currency risk
or toxic infantry to dealer too
we know what happens yeah
it results in that hot potato trading
now what about then
if a client came to bank here
this client is a worthy client.
They're a valued client.
The client wants to fill 60 million.
Big transaction.
Client instructs the bank to fill 60 million.
Banks like, fuck that.
We can't take 60 million risk on like that.
We need to hedge it.
So Bank One goes into EBS and lifts 60 million.
They're pushing 60 million.
When one million is filled here, they fill one million.
When 60 million is done, they fill 60 million.
Did you get it?
In that process,
imagine hot potato trading kicked off
so this guy brought 60 million
he brought it off this guy
this guy sold he's now short
he needs to get out short position
because price is moving against him
and he doesn't want to be short
if one of his competitors is long
so he longs it
this guy's short he longs it this guy's short
everybody's longing now yeah
price is moving up now
where the prices are set
prices are made here
prices are moving up
the original client
getting worse and worse and worse prices.
The volatility, basically, was greater back then
because of this information that's leaking.
The client's order flow information was leaking onto this platform
where all these other liquidity providers would then respond
and cause greater and higher execution costs for the original client
as a result of information leakage.
So that was one of the problems EBS posed.
Do you get it?
Imagine that when this client goes long in a second scenario, he goes along 60 million with a bank.
The bank decides to fill him 60 million, and none of that 60 million ever, ever reaches the EBS market.
The bank just deals with that risk in a different way.
None of these other banks are wiser.
They never, ever know about that transaction that just occurred, who it occurred from, what size that volume was.
never ever find out about it.
There's less information that leaked.
Meaning lower information leakage,
price moves less against,
adversity against this guy's,
you know,
he's trying to buy.
He wants price to not move up as much as possible.
He wants to buy it at the price he's trying to buy up,
right?
He doesn't want slippage, basically.
And because information isn't leaking,
it causes less slippage
and this guy gets a better execution.
But as of right now,
this 1990s part of,
of FX, information was leaking quite frequently through EBS, resulting in hot potato trading,
very, very important part and implication of trading through EBS, where all the volume kind of,
a good majority of it was trading through EBS. Another point to make here is this client's 60 million
ended up eventually on EBS and the price has started to move there and then the rest of these guys
would have responded. And there's obviously this guy would have responded as well in his
prices. So what I'm saying is volume, price change on EBS. So information is embedded, put into EBS,
EBS forms the price, and then that price is reflected back out to the market. In other words,
those who were sitting on EBS had an informational advantage over the end receivers of the price,
because information came to EBS first, imagine a bus route, first stop, and then second
stop back out to market. The first stop gets picked up quicker. The information reaches the
first stop. The bus reaches the first stop quicker. The information reaches EBS quicker first.
Price changes there first and then goes back out to the market. Imagine that difference
was one second. Imagine within that second you could trade a million times, a thousand
times a hundred times man you're
fucking years ahead of the market
you get it but
I wasn't necessarily the case back then banks
back in 1990s they didn't
have hence why
you know EBS had to come through
but in 1990s they didn't have the
necessary infrastructure to kind of take advantage
of that information in one second
they definitely had information on the advantages
over their clients definitely
they knew more about currency
they knew more about who would decide stronger
weaker but they didn't
necessarily have the technological
capabilities to exploit the
one, two second differences as they do
today. All right?
But one of the important points
I'm also raising here is
that you have interbank
connected to EBS
and that is only for the
interbank banks. And then
you had the tier two of the market where those
prices are pushed out to here.
All right, let me introduce you to
another fucking issue that clients
had. Each bank is a market.
maker, a liquidity provider, they have a bid and ask, yeah?
What's the best bid, best offer?
You don't know?
You don't know.
As a client, yeah?
Because as a client who's here, you can't fucking see what's on EBS, not part of it.
However, you have one bank, two bank, three bank, four banks giving you all different
prices.
The problem is, this guy's sell price might be cheaper.
This guy's sell price might be the most competitive.
They're two different banks.
Theoretically, you'd think if you just go buy there or whatever, right?
Yeah. The problem is to trade with a bank, you need a relationship with it. To trade with a bank, you settle in two days, which means you need credit relationship. In other words, if I am a client of the bank, it's not just a piece of paper, hey, you're my client. No, you deposit margin with them. Just like you have margin with your broker. You deposit margin with bank one. So this client has 500, a small amount. That's a very, very small amount of margin, very small, but 500K.
And then one day it turns out that Bank 4 has consistently cheaper prices on the ASC
and Bank 1 has consistently cheaper prices on the bid.
Well, if client fucking 4 wants to trade here, he needs to deposit another 500K with him.
And then if he wants to trade another bank, he needs to deposit another 500K with him.
Now this guy's got 1.5 million exposure just in margin across three risk-taking institutions
who might go bust at any time.
he has three different counterparty
and default risks
yeah that's a lot of risk
yeah basically
risk is high
so there's now another
gap in the market
what if this client
could access all the bank's quotes
but just through one bank
because like I said
these banks have credit relationships
with each other
yeah
right so maybe this client
can just be a client of bank one
and if he wants to trade at bank four's quote
bank one will do it for him through him
he will trade at bank four's quote through bank one
on bank one's name on bank one's relationship
so if you came to notting them
and you didn't know someone
all right you didn't know anyone
and I don't know how to take
that's not a great analogy imagine
you have a shop on the high street yeah
and you need to get some
okay not a great fucking analogy
but anyway the point of making is
you might have relationships with someone
that sells weed
you sell weed as well
I need to access some weed
but you haven't got it
maybe I can go through you
to your boy and get weed from him
right
so I rode on your name
and your relationship
maybe your boy never knew
it was me behind it
maybe me and your boy had beef
but at the end of the day
I went through you
you went to pick up the PIF
you did all the money transactions
and whatnot and then you eventually come back to me
and you might take a few grams
right
that's you're essentially
brokering that situation
yeah
it's called prime brokerage
but doesn't that like
so for example in that bank one
doesn't he get anything out of
yeah
oh he does okay
so look
The point I'm making here is there was a gap in the market.
EBS originally fixed that gap in the market for credit intermediation and connecting banks together.
They took some market share away from them.
Each transaction that happens on EPS, EPS probably takes a small, small commission.
If you trade a million, which is 10 lots, it's probably going to be about $60, $60 you pay.
$30 in, $30 out, $60 you pay.
If you trade $1 million on EBS, it's probably like $1 or $2 at the bank's pay.
For call.
Okay.
So even though EBS makes a lot of transactions or facilitates a lot of transactions,
they're still capturing some market shares.
They're still capturing some money from it.
Bank, they have services.
They have a market-making service, liquidity providing service, the same thing.
But now there's this gap in the market.
They can connect this client to all the other banks as a potential another revenue stream.
It's another part of their business they can offer.
So yeah, they do make money from it.
It's a revenue stream and they'll capture commissions, at least commissions, from the volume traded.
Also, the client who's a prime, basically that service is called prime brokerage, right?
What we're going to say?
Yeah, you have to post margins still.
You have to post margin.
Now, the problem is back then, or at least, so what happened in 2000s is internet kind of blew up
from 2000, 2000, and 3, et cetera,
the internet blew up.
And retail outfits,
so small brokers, start to offer an internet,
yeah, so retail outfits started to offer effects
and trading services, really,
to retail clients.
That's where really the retail market started to blow up.
Do you get it?
Now, obviously, if I'm a broker,
so imagine I set up a brokerage,
where do I get my quotes from?
Well, theoretically, you know, I can go to a bank.
The bank sells quotes.
They sell liquidity.
I'm buying liquidity.
I'm reselling it to the client, to my retail client.
But originally I'm buying liquidity and later selling it on.
But sometimes brokers, they want to get the best prices from all the banks.
So they would also apply for the prime brokerage, part of the bank.
And they would be able to access all of these quotes from all the other banks, take the best bid, best offer,
resell it onto their client by adding on a spread, right?
So Bank One has a bid and ask with a spread of 0.9 pips.
Bank two has a spread of four pips, bid and ask, and six pips spread, seven pips spread, whatever.
The tighter spreads happen to be with bank one.
The broker can take that spread for himself and really,
sell that liquidity to you with a five hip spread. So in other words, here's a bid, here's
a ask. If you want to buy as a retail client at my brokerage firm, you buy on the ask
price, which is here. However, the broker can immediately hedge your trade at a much,
much, much, much cheaper price. So when you buy, I sell to you. I sell to you at a price where
I've added the spread on.
Basically, I've increased the price.
However, I can, so, you know, I need actual numbers for this.
So we're going to look at fucking something simple.
GbPUST.
It's quite simple.
So let's just say GbPUST was 1.3164.
That's the bid.
1.3165.
That's a one-p spread.
This bank was 644, all the way to,
6.8.
That's a
3.6 pip spread.
Yeah?
Et cetera, et cetera.
What is the best
prices for the bid
and one of the best prices
for the ask in this market?
In the first one?
Yeah.
So, no, no, no, it's not.
It's not.
What's the best, what's the best
bid, best offer?
Not the spread, the best fit, best offer.
Oh.
Yeah, second.
Yeah.
The spread's better in the first
but the offers bear in the second
no
the bid from the second
the offer from the first
wait hold on
so this guy is buying at the most expensive price
and this guy's selling at the cheapest price
oh okay I couldn't see the
the figures of the
yeah I couldn't see that
yeah so that's that's
bank one that's a bid
that's a bid one from bank one
and then the bank two has
31644 which is
higher that's bank two and then on the offer side bank one has 3165 and this guy has 3168 so that's bank
two that's bank one bank two has the most expensive bid bank one has the cheapest offer that's the
best bid best offer you get it yeah the real spread is 0.6 pips you follow me
that's what this broker can access through prime brokerage.
So he takes this best bid, best offer.
31644, 3165.
What's in between that?
That's 0.6 in between.
The middle price then becomes 35, 36, 37.
Let's just call it 3167.
You follow me?
That's the mid price.
He adds 2.5 pips there.
He minuses 2.5 pips there.
What's that?
3167, 31695.
That's the offer.
31645.
That's the bid, I think.
Yeah, that's the bid.
These are the prices you're getting.
These are the prices I'm giving to you.
Can you see how there's a 5 pip spread between that?
Really, the broker can access a 0.6 pip spread.
me, I can access
0.6 pips spread
but because you're buying
off me and I'm buying off the bank
I'm going to sell it to you for more expensive
I sell it to you with a 5 pip spread
you follow me
so when you buy
you buy at 3169
I short at 3169
I immediately go to the bank
and I buy at 3165
I capture 4.5 pips
like that
you got filled at that
you got filled at the
spread that you accepted as a retail client. I had direct access to the to the bank. I got a better
price and I hedged the risk straight away. If I wanted to, if I, you know, did you get it?
Yeah. Basically, I'm saying brokers add on a spread to the, to the prices that they get from
the market. The market is the interbank. Anyway, what happened is banks got too complacent with
handing out these prime brokerage relationships
to anybody, you have to remember
with a prime brokerage relationship,
they're giving you access to all these other banks.
They're also giving you access to credit.
So here's a prime brokerage.
I'm a broker.
The prime brokerage says,
give us 100 million.
And in exchange,
you can open up up to
$5 billion worth of exposure
at any given time.
You know what that is?
That works out to be
50 times leverage,
50 to one leverage.
That's what it is.
The prime brokerage is saying,
give us 100 million.
That's 100,000.
What I'm saying?
100,000, yeah?
Whatever it is.
100 million is what it's meant to be.
And if you post 100 million with us in cash,
we will, in exchange,
you give you $5 billion worth of exposure.
So you can open up a transaction.
transaction with $5 billion, and your margin is $100 million.
Do you get it?
Yeah.
It's 50 to one leverage.
That's just an example.
So in exchange, this broker can actually access billions in leverage on the prime brokerage
relationship, just the same way.
If you have 500 to one leverage on IC markets, you can post 200, 200 pound-ish, or $200,
and open up one lot, which is 100K.
yeah all right so they're just given them access to leverage the posting of real margin for that obviously you have to maintain the correct margin levels and they're able to access equity from the other banks and I'll leave you at that right and we'll leave you at that next session we're going to discuss how doing this allowed some information to be hidden at least the client's identity is hidden we're also going to discuss our prime brokerage blew up
Some banks took on too much risk.
In 2015, some brokers owed banks up to $300 million.
FXM owed their prime broker $300 million.
They had to take a loan now for $300 million.
A new investor came, brought the company,
got them out of $300 million, how we'll give it a loan, basically.
And that's how FXCM still survived today.
In 2015, they got fucked by a flash crash in the Swiss franc.
So the main takeaway is, hopefully you remember this, the structure of the market, trading through EBS, helped it a bit, allowed the banks to offload risk quicker and, you know, the efficiency of price distribution was increased. However, information leakage became more prominent. The information game became more competitive. Banks increased the informational advantage over the rest of the market because prices were made here and then redistribute it.
back out to the market.
This is where prices were formed.
You call that price discovery.
Prices were discovered, formed, made on EBS.
Banks were seeing that first, like the first stop on the bus route.
And then the second, you know, the price was going to the second stop.
All right.
And then prime brokerage allowed bank clients, this client, to access liquidity from all
the other banks.
And we're going to discuss a very, very, yeah.
We're going to discuss the effects of that.
Eventually turned out that clients could now trade on EBS.
Now, think about it.
If clients in the secondary market can see prices being made here first,
imagine they had the technological capacity.
I hope you understand.
So EBS is where prices are made.
Here's the customer segment.
Imagine the customer, this one customer,
could see where the prices are being made.
It obviously takes time for EBS prices to get made
and then the bank to adjust their prices
and resell it back out.
This takes time.
Imagine this client who could see it first here.
By the time it sent out to the market
could take advantage of that information.
Yeah, we'll be a very rich person.
All right, so that's what you call
what HF, basically high-frequency trading systems
can do that.
There was one HFT firm up to 2008
in how many trading years?
I think they had one trading loss
or one trading day that lost
in a whole year.
In a whole year.
HFT loses one day
is a very, very big firm.
Virtue HFD had only one losing date,
Business Insider.
In 1,238 days,
that's 300,
that's four fucking years bro
one lost in four years
one losing day
in four years
that's the type of edge
we're talking about
when you operate on a
sub-second scale
yeah
do you get it
also next session
I'll discuss with you
how co-location
so how high-frequency traders
or systems at least
position themselves
closer
to the exchange
and they would receive updates
about price changes first
before this client and these guys
could front run and take advantage of prices
that's basically the reason that virtue
firm would have only
had one losing day. It's ridiculous.
So think about all this shit
for a minute and then think about the guy that sits
at home, draws a trend line, tries to buy this
like this and then
when the market does that
he tries to
I don't know, whatever the fuck he does, yeah, but the effect that the reason price accelerates like this
is because of some of the behaviors that these guys, you know, the behaviors of these guys
and the systems through which they trade.
It was through EBS where prices were formed, then it changes a bit.
The technological capacity of these guys increased over time as they tried to keep market share.
That has an effect on how liquidity is provided.
All of these things are the reason you see.
these prices that you see here.
These prices that you see in here are profoundly different
with the prices that you'd see,
at least the volatility is different,
that you would have seen here.
Let me try to pull up something,
I'll let you go, average tree range,
you'll do it 14-day period.
So prices, you know, on average are moving.
The lowest here that's moving is 59 pips a day.
166 pips a day is moving there.
In between about 140 pips here, 140 pips a day, average in around this region.
We go back, obviously in financial crisis, it peaked at 400 pips a day.
Pre-financial crisis, we're talking median probably about 150 pips a day, quite a nice median.
The lowest, obviously, hit 90 pips a day.
Fast forward to the last like five years.
the highest is hitting, 300 pips a day, probably average and median 111 pips a day, 120 pips a day.
This is GPP UST, one of the most volatile peers of the last five years.
If I showed you your USD, it was down at 50 pips a day, bro.
The reason GBP is volatile, like I said, risk asset at this point in time, because of Brexit and the way it's behaving.
But really, fuck it.
Just show you your USD quickly.
fucking platform
I thought the screen froze then
no no no
alright here we go
alright so we were down
to like 50 pips a day
here for a whole year
for a whole
motherfucking year bro
50 pips a day
let draw a median line
fuck it
well really so
maybe that
you know
100 pips a day
go back to
pre-2008
oh shit it's quite low there you know
but still
price as you can see
the median around this period at least
was probably that
no
probably somewhere like there
which is obviously
a significant amount
oh shit
109 pips
110 pips
still quite low
back in 2004
but compare that
basically
to this
where it's much much lower
the average
do you get it
Yeah, much lower than compared to before.
And you have these periods where there's absolutely no volatility for sustained periods, I guess.
There's more a function of market, of market changes, evolution of the market.
But again, we'll discuss that.
Anyway, I'll leave it at that.
If you have any questions, let me know.